Guide to the Theodore James Holmes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Theodore James Holmes papers
1846-1910
MS 831
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
The most significant part of the papers consists of the correspondence of Holmes and his wife, Ellen Holmes, between 1863 and 1865 during his service as chaplain in the 1st Connecticut Cavalry. Also in the papers are correspondence, minutes of meetings and resolutions relating to church affairs, 1859-1893.
Holmes, Theodore James, 1833-1906
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret Owen, 1978.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Most of the letters included in the papers were written by Theodore to his wife, a few by her to her parents. The plan apparently was to make a formal Journal to cover his war experiences. He wrote frequently and fully to Ellen and she copied the letters, slightly edited, into the Journal. The existing letters, however, cover only a part of the war period; gaps in the account are filled by entries from the Journal.
The Alfred mentioned by Ellen was her younger brother. Theodore mentions his sister Julia, and his brothers Louis, Charlie, and Frank. The Olmsteds in East Hartford were life-long friends. The word "contraband" refers to escaped slaves. (Margaret Owen, 1978).
Biographical / Historical
Theodore James Holmes was born in Utica, New York, April 26, 1833, the son of Sylvanus and Elizabeth Hoyt Holmes. He graduated from Yale College in 1853, taught for three years in the Asylum for the Deaf and Dumb in Hartford, and then entered Union Theological Seminary. After graduation in 1859 he went to a mission church in Richmond, Vermont, and in 1861 was called to the Congregational Church in East Hartford, Connecticut. In the same year he married Ellen Louisa Goldsmith, who was born in Little Compton, Rhode Island, December 26, 1841, the daughter of Reverend Alfred and Sarah Merrill Goldsmith. In 1863 Theodore was granted a leave of absence to enlist in the Union forces and was commissioned Chaplain in the 1st Connecticut Cavalry and served until his resignation in 1865. He returned to East Hartford where he remained until 1873. He later held pastorates in Brooklyn, Baltimore, Newton Center, Hopkinton, Massachusetts, and finally returned to Richmond, Vermont for the last few years of his active ministry. He died in Concord, New Hampshire in 1906. (Margaret Owen, donor, 1978).
Military chaplains; Religion; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Diaries; Clergy; Holmes, Ellen Louise Goldsmith, b. 1841; Holmes, Theodore James, 1833-1906; United States. Army. Connecticut Cavalry Regiment, 1st (1861-1865)
- Inventory
  - Civil War correspondence of TJH and of his wife Ellen Louisa Goldsmith Holmes, 1863 November 24-1864 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Civil War correspondence of TJH and of his wife Ellen Louisa Goldsmith Holmes, 1864 July 22-1865 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Civil War journal with correspondence and military orders bound in, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of the journal and of the letters of TJH and of his wife Ellen Holmes, 1863-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Civil War memorabilia (See also: MG Common folio, No. 19), 1864, 1866, 1906, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Church correspondence, 1861-1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Church minutes of meetings, resolutions, 1859-1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Posthumous tributes, 1906, 1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1864, 1869, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (2) of TJH, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Student memorabilia, 1846-1847, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diplomas: Yale BA 1853, Yale MA 1856, Union Theological Seminary 1859
  - Printed material: First Congregational Church, East Hartford, Conn., 1702-1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed material: The Eclectic Club of Baltimore: A Historical Sketch, by Oliver Huckel, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Seminary diploma, Yale diploma, 1859 (Box 2)